[Music]
okay so I'm here today to give a talk
about money and our monetary system and
what I want to do is talk first of all
about how money is created there are
three different kinds of money I'll
briefly talk about each one but I want
to particularly focus on commercial bank
money because that is over ninety seven
percent of the money supply is
commercial bank money and that is really
that's a hub that at the hub of our
monetary system so I don't explain where
it where money comes from how it works
and how it is used to transfer wealth
from the poor in everything it never to
be up to the rich how it inevitably
creates unpayable debt which we all then
have to pay off using our labor using
our work using our love and our
creativity basically giving our lives
away to the man so first of all what is
money like I said there are three
different kinds of money the first kind
of money is government money this is the
cash this is the notes and coins that
we're all familiar with in circulation
what we all you know think of as money
but actually this only account for about
two-and-a-half percent of our total
money supply so government money is
printed at the Royal Mint and then those
notes and coins are sold through the
commercial banks and and circulated
through the commercial high excellences
it's important to understand that
government money is issued it's paid for
and it goes into circulation
it is not gathering interest it is not
owned to anyone by anyone this is
debt-free money interest free money but
like I said this is only about two and a
half percent of the total money in
circulation the other 97% is commercial
bank money I'm going to talk a lot about
that in just a minute but just before I
do let me talk about the third kind of
money first kind of money is central
bank money we don't ever see that
central bank money is held in the Bank
of England and is
at the end of each trading day to settle
accounts between the commercial banks
commercial bank money this is what I
want to spend most of my time because
this is the really evil part of our
monetary system if you have a banking
license you are granted the permission
through your brother permission to
create money in response to a loan so a
customer goes into a bank and they want
to borrow a hundred thousand pounds to
buy a house the bank in response to
those needs for that loan create house
of thin air a hundred thousand brand-new
signee pounds not notes and coins it is
just a bookkeeping entry they tap a
hundred thousand pounds credit into your
bank account and at the same time you
now have created a debt with the bank
you owe the bank one hundred thousand
pounds plus the interest over the period
of time and that under our commercial
banking system money and debt are in
fact the same thing money given to you
by the bank is equal to debt owed by you
to the bank so money equals that's a
really important concept to remember
here I'm going to come back to this
theme again and again during the
renewing the course of my talk so you go
to the bank and you borrow 100,000
pounds I will represent that hundred
thousand pounds as that block you now
owe the bank one hundred thousand pounds
they have a debt owed to them four
hundred thousand pounds now believe it
or not once the bank lends you that
money which remember they never had in
the first place they've created it out
of thin air that debt now becomes an
asset of the bank believe it or not yeah
they are owed this money
barefoot becomes an asset of the bank
now they've lend you that money and so
on top of that loan you're going to have
to pay interest so the debt is bigger
than the amount of money lent you write
this is the amount of money in
circulation this is the debt oh another
person comes along bros 100,000 pounds
another 100,000 pounds owed to the bank
plus the interest on that hundred
thousand pounds you can see that as more
and more money is lent the difference
between the money lent and the money
owed is forever getting bigger and
bigger and bigger you can see on these
two bars there's now three hundred
thousand pounds in circulation but
there's four or five hundred thousand
pounds
owes to the banks right now this is the
fruit this is one of the crucial things
to understand about our monetary system
is that there is never enough money in
circulation to cover all of the debt
which is owed as at 2010 this will blow
your mind and if it doesn't blow your
mind you're not fully understanding it
sorry I don't mean that to sound
patronizing but that's that decayed as
of 2010 around the world global debt
total global debt was 180 trillion
dollars that was in 2010 in 2010 the
global money supply was about 70
trillion dollars so I was at 2010 this
problem here with because there's
interest you on debt this problem here
of debt being bigger than money in
circulation has got to the point where
there was in 2010
100 and trillion dollars 110 sorry
trillion dollars around the world of
debt which simply cannot be paid because
the money to pay it does not exist right
it's like a game of musical chairs
you've got three chairs in the game but
you've got five players in the game two
of those players when the music stops
two of those players are going to be
left out in the cold in other words
defaults bankruptcies people not being
able to pay their mortgages businesses
not being able to service their debt
this kind of thing is inevitable because
the interest payments soon get to a
point you know you've got so much more
debt than money in circulation that some
people must default on their debt now
what happens when a debt is paid when a
debt is paid and then that's always been
money and debt because they're opposites
of each other when you pay off your debt
the money is destroyed the money in the
debt cancel each other out when debt is
paid money is destroyed so all this
nonsense they talk you hear on the news
government representatives the
Chancellor of Exchequer even doesn't
understand this basic point it is
impossible to reduce the deficit it's
impossible to pay off the national debt
because the money to do so simply
doesn't exist the only way to keep up
with the ever expanding
interest payments on this unpayable that
is to create ever more and ever more
money and of course as you create more
money you're creating more debt
alongside that money you can never ever
ever get ahead of the curve and I don't
mean it's impossible in the sense of you
know it's not actually impossible I mean
the actual dictionary definition of
impossible it simply cannot be done
right so that's consequence number one
is debt slavery sorry its consequence
number one is unpayable debt being built
up in the economy consequence number two
is that though real wealth in the
economy always being transferred from
poor people to rich people from ordinary
working folk to the banks how do they
write okay if you don't mind I'm going
to talk a little bit about solutions at
the end if you don't mind but yeah but
you may know this I think there are an
awful lot of people out there that don't
so I'm trying to elucidate the problems
first and then I'll talk about some one
possible there are a wide range of
possible solutions like for example
universal basic income you know removing
the need for giving your labor to sister
to sustain the basic essentials of life
as I say there are lots of ideas out
there none of them are perfect they all
have their good points in there bad
point I'm just saying that until lots of
people are aware of the problems and
understand the need to find solutions
and the sorry say again sit for
thousands of years I know but what stood
between now and any time in history is
our ability to communicate with each
other a large scale anywhere in the
world instantly by the internet we've
never had the internet before right
that's what's different now and that's
what gives me possible hope for the
future is that we can find ways to
collaborate with each other on a large
scale independently the banks and the
government's and hopefully make them
irrelevant and obsolete that's yet short
I realize it seems like a bit of a pipe
dream but if you can't even hope for it
you can't even conceive it what hope do
you ever have of bringing it into
reality do you not I mean so can we try
and be a bit up being a bit hopeful
rather than negative right because if we
say there's nothing we can do then for
sure we're never going to do anything
you know what I mean you understand I'm
saying right anyway so next thing is the
transference of wealth from the poor to
the rich inevitably because think about
it who has money to
rich people who needs money poor people
so what ends up happening is poor people
pay interest to rich people making poor
people ever poorer and rich people ever
rich I'm just a little just a little
stacked to reinforce that idea about
transferring real wealth from the poor
to the rich in 1960 the top 20% of
people had 30 times the wealth of the
bottom 20% in 1998 that ratio increased
to 74 times in the u.s. in 90 2007 the
top 1% own 42 percent of the nation's
wealth the bottom 80% between them own 7
percent just a couple of months ago in
the news there was the stat about the
richest 8 people in the world now have
as much wealth as the poorest 50 percent
of the people in the world so this gap
this inequality gap between rich and
poor has been growing larger and larger
and it is inevitable this is not about
really people taking more for themselves
this is systemic it is not it is
unavoidable under this monetary system
for this wealth gap between rich and
poor to increase forever it simply can't
be stopped
third consequence of our monetary system
because we're constantly creating new
money and bringing it into circulation
all of that new money has to go
somewhere right it has to be spent
somewhere and so two things about this
firstly inflation we are taught we tend
to think about inflation as being about
rising prices it's not that is a sip not
a cause and inflation the reason for
inflation is the constantly expanding
number of pounds in circulation you're
increasing the number of pounds flowing
around then you've got to do one of two
things you either have to increase the
number of goods and services available
in the economy or the price of those
existing goods and services has to go up
to reflect the extra money that's
circulating about this is called
inflation when prices go up this is
called inflation but it's a consequence
of an expanding money supply not a
consequence of rising prices the other
thing and more importantly if if a bank
is deciding where they're going to lend
their money they decide where money is
being spent in society they do not lend
money on high risk they do not lend
money on high risk ventures they will
lend money on Shore things and so what's
happened positive easing
and the bailout money to the banks where
did that go did that go on
infrastructure development does that go
on transportation if you're lowering
transportation costs or energy cost of
people did that go on building more
social housing it didn't go on any of
those things it went on reinflates in
the housing markets we've got another
housing bubble that we're now in the
midst of it went to inflation the stock
market's record highs and it went to
speculating on the foreign exchange
market you know over four trillion
dollars is traded every day on the
foreign exchange market global GDP is
about 70 trillion dollars four trillion
dollars is traded every day on the
foreign exchange markets it's nonsense
it's got completely out of control all
of that money floating around is being
used to service rich people it's not
going to us down here right the forgive
me just referring to notes again I have
done this book before believe it or not
but for some reason my mind is blanking
today and sorry say again yeah right and
then yeah finally is the concept of debt
slavery and this is this is really what
I'm all about is we are slaves to the
banks here basically every minute that
you work you are working primarily for
the banks you get to keep very very
little of your own bit bearing in mind
at the banks can make money out of thin
air right so they are taking no risk
when they lend you a hundred thousand
pounds to buy your health they are
taking no risk they're creating money
out of thin air
they didn't own the money as property in
the first place right if you default on
your mortgage they take the house they
take the whole house including any
deposit you pay including any increase
in value of the house including any
mortgage payments you've made so far
they take the whole house from you not
only the unpaid portion of it they are
taking no risk here so what you do you
go and borrow money from the bank but
you have to repay that money with real
labor with real time with real love they
are essentially stealing your life away
from you turning it into a debt and then
making you spend your life repaying that
debt to them debt based currency is
simply a path to slavery I don't just
mean on
individual-level this happens at a
governmental level as well we've now got
into a situation where bank assets are
some five hundred and fifty percent of
national GDP every year up until the
1960s 1970s it's been pretty steady at
about 40 percent the banks now have five
hundred and fifty percent of the the
banks has to five hundred fifty percent
of global GDP what this means it and
most of those assets are government
bonds what you've got is commercial
banks creating money out of thin air
lending them back to national
governments at interest in exchange for
government bonds those bonds carry
interest how does the government pay the
interest on those bonds out of our taxes
did you know and again this will blow
your mind did you know that 90% of the
income tax revenue collected by the
Treasury goes to paying interest on the
national debt it does not go toward
building roads and schools and hospitals
and improving the energy infrastructure
ninety percent notable tax revenue
you're talking about income tax revenue
ninety percent of income tax revenue
goes towards paying interest on loans
from commercial banks the government is
paying interest to commercial banks for
money to which it is the sole issuing
authority remember the Bank of England
is the only one that has the authority
to issue money and it has the authority
to issue the mercial banks to issue
money but the commercial banks are
creating funny money out of thin air
lending it back to government in
hundreds of billions in trillions of
dollars and government are now paying
interest on those debt through the
taxation of its citizens the IRS sorry
the Federal Reserve vote was set up in
1913 the IRS the American
Inland Revenue Service was also set up
in 1913 right so as the Federal Reserve
was set up to lend money to government
the government also set up a tax
collection service so it could start
making interest payments on the loan but
it was taken from a private bank the
Federal Reserve is not a federal agency
it is a private bank despite what they
call themselves
correct it's owned by a cabal of private
bankers so what this means is because
banks are holding hundreds of billions
or even trillions of government debt
bacon now dictate terms to government
they can tell government what they can
and can't spend money on they can tell
government that they have to enter into
cost-cutting measures right they can
tell government what they can and can't
do for their citizens
so actually our governments are no
longer running things even if their
desire to make life better for their
citizens were sincere and they're not
but even if they had a sincere desire to
make life better for their citizens they
simply cannot do so because they are in
hock up to their eyeballs to the banks
right so the question now becomes as the
gentleman over here was asking before
firstly why is it like this how does it
come about well it's very simple money
men have always pulled the strings for
thousands of years yeah the Pharos
further the kings and queens the
Emperor's the conquerors you know these
are all the people at the very very top
of always been those that have pulled
the strings this is nothing new and so
on modern banking system our modern
modern mantra is simply a very clever
very sophisticated way of keeping the
population enslaved without them even
knowing that they are enslaved as Johann
Wolfgang von Goethe wrote none are so
hopelessly enslaved as those who falsely
believed themselves to be free and sadly
that is how I see that is how I see what
we are unfortunately unwitting slave to
the man right so solutions what we do
about it and unfortunately until many
many many more people see that there is
a problem there is not going to be any
serious search for solutions but there
are people out there we've been trying
very very hard to come up with
alternatives so did you hear something
yeah go ahead
it's a collective collective thing right
so ultimately I guess it's a computer
kind of that's that's allocating things
but it's doing so according to an agreed
scheme as to what's there and what
equitable and what's needed you know to
me and so a large part of a
resource-based economy is based on
shared access the thing not everybody
has a car right you don't need to have a
car 80% of the time 90% of a power cut
your fuel cars are parked there right so
you don't need to own a car
what you need is access to a car when
you need one right and so again with
modern systems is not difficult to set
up an uber style system where you ring
up a car come pick you up tastes where
you're going goes on picks up the next
buses
nobody needs to own a car anyway nor me
and this can apply to many many many
things this concept of shared ownership
[Laughter]
[Music]
it's a good example of decreasing
correct exactly right in the end
someone has to control as you say who
will
be able to create that yeah sorry to
interrupt you but you're upset and this
is this is the number one criticism of
the idea of results based economy is
it's still a centralized control system
right and a resource-based economy
cannot come about without us first
experiencing a change in consciousness
right where we stop seeing each other as
competition and we start seeing each
other as brothers and sister right and
until that comes about a resource-based
economy cannot happen but for the
long-term sustainable good of mankind
something along the line of resource
based economy has to be has to be the
way forward right even though it's
difficult to see it from where we are
now yes go on well okay in what we need
I mean a resource-based economy or
something like it I really think the
long-term future of mankind is where we
need to end up how we get from here to
there
transitional solutions their replacement
yeah I agree you offered you asked the
most difficult question and there are
lots of transitional ideas out there so
moving away from it step number one step
number one is to move away from a debt
based monetary system yeah something is
not rooted in depth gold Bitcoin
government-issued currency whatever but
something which is not rooted in debt no
no I agree to get straight from here to
a resource-based economy it's impossible
you can't do it in one step right there
has to be a series of transition step I
completely agree with you right so step
number one on this road is to get rid of
debt based currencies and replace it
with currencies which are not rooted in
debt which are not controlled and issued
by a commercial bank that are
independent of all of that for example
gold for example Bitcoin right these are
outside you can't create gold you can't
just make gold out of thin air right
there's a finite amount of it
same with Bitcoin you know that
something like that is it is a step on
the road toward the idea of a universal
basic income so that people are removed
from slavery you don't have to work to
feed yourself to house yourself you know
what I mean that that again is a step on
the road but these are all transitions
these are all ways of getting to the
final goal which is no money because we
don't need it we don't need if you have
unfettered access to everything that you
need and the freedom to follow your
passions and do what you want to what
hell's you need money for do you know
what I mean it's like a Star Trek sort
of thing what the hell do you need money
for not necessary what I said if you
mean example you need money for in your
life give me an example of something you
need money for I'd say okay let me let
me give you an example let's say that
you're a business right you want to
build a new factory you've got a need
for iguana yeah so you need money to buy
the land and build the factory but you
don't need the money what you need is
the space you need people to build the
buildings you need the material to visit
a building that's what you need right
you need that much do you need the
machines to tool the factory need to
train the workers in how to use the
machinery this is what you need right
now right now under our system money is
a vehicle by which you do these things
right but you don't actually need the
money what you need is those things and
so we need to get away is this mode of
thinking where money directs everything
because money is a fantasy we made it up
yeah it's like the boogeyman it's like
the tooth fairy's like Santa Claus here
we made it up and we can just as easily
forget about yeah I need a little baby I
agree but if you live in a society where
everybody is motivated simply to help
each other out where they can because
that's how we all live now right yeah
and that's what I'm talking about the
change of consciousness I'm talking
about right and until we get that we
can't get rid of money you're right we
need to change our thinking first then
we can change those systems but that is
up to every individual I can't change
your thinking right every individual has
to take responsibility for how they act
in this world how they treat the people
around them how they treat the planet
around them you don't mean every
individual person must take
responsibility for that and must try in
a gentle loving way when they see other
people not doing that to try and put
them on the right path in order me not
beat them into it not shout them into it
gently lovingly just try and show them
because everybody has to come to it
themselves yeah if you try and force it
on people they will simply back away
from it you know
yeah and so everything's yeah we're all
one we're all one fucking being on this
planet right to treat us each other with
anything other than compassion and love
and respect is stupid as simple as that
right you don't need religion to tell
you that you don't need laws to tell you
that we all know that it's self-evident
right obvious we all know that so let's
act like that right let's be like that
every single minute in this world let's
be like that but forget government
solutions you're not planning from the
top down solutions are not coming that
way we have to find solution ourselves
and make them irrelevant and obsolete so
stop that ignore them do your own thing
make them irrelevant and obsolete
let them fade away into nothingness
where they belong that's all they're
interested is preserving their own power
right so they are not going to provide
solutions we the middle class in rich
countries it is up to us to save the
world no one else is going to do it I'm
telling you I know that sounds
incredibly elitist but it is up to us
the middle and working class people in
rich countries we are the only ones who
have the power to bring about real
change in this world
it's up to us by doing things like this
by going to gatherings and spreading the
word of love yeah all you can do then
they shoot me you know what I mean then
they shoot me
so what won't you you've got no more
problems but you know what once you want
it once you understand once you
understand how rapacious and evil the
system that we live in is and how hard
it is to break from how can you having
it not be the thing that's at the front
of your mind in the front of your heart
every minute of every day to try and
change that to try and change as many
hearts and souls as you can with every
waking minute what higher purpose could
there be for your living on this height
in this time in this play day for each
and every one of us who sees the problem
as it is we have some model we have to
be beacons to all of those around as we
have to model that compassion on that
understanding and that love to each
other he's still good talking about it
then do it just use all you can do is
you do it in your life every minute of
every day you do it that's all you can
be responsible for right you can't
change the world Bobby Kennedy and I'm
paraphrasing it I'm not I'm not going to
get this worth word Bobby Kennedy said
that few of us will have the ability to
achieve greatness tonight but every
single one of us in effect in some small
way what goes on in our little world and
in the sum of all of those actions can
be the doing over generalities yes sorry
go on
correct because it is good to do so and
it feels good to do so absolutely right
nobody plays the game has to stop right
absolutely
I have to say this man here respected
him he's got the balls to actually not
play their game at all
he just doesn't play at all I would love
to have to have those kinds of balls
myself I really would
yeah but work but way way way less than
the rest of us right now resource base
on the monterey go we're just passing
through doesn't belong to anyone
properties rolled out they absolutely it
all of life doesn't even belong to all
of life it is simply a home for all as
long as you don't see there is product
so somewhere no one lies we claimed
ownership over something sauce and then
we use those for exactly right to
control each other's money that's
exactly right so if you want to get away
we can't find a way of giving it all
back absolute and aiding i only say it
as a transition that's all not as a
final solution
absolutely dropping systems that we had
completely valuing life above everything
else
surely are actually mine I couldn't have
said it any any possibly bettered
exactly lights what I meant about a
transformation in consciousness do you
guys know any society or place on earth
technical people team in Israel they
have a play have a pretty and prettier
guys pretty egalitarian there if you
read there's a bike with David Graeber
who writes quite extensively about you
know sort of prehistoric man he's an
anthropologist and he writes quite
extensively about ways societies were
organized and according to him back in
the hunter-gatherer societies were
entirely in Gannet area I mean there
wasn't hierarchical structure at all and
he also believed but the idea of barter
isn't there was no widespread system at
Bartle before money money came in in one
step as a way to control and organize
populations as nations and empires
started to us money was a way of
controlling your citizenry you know what
I mean
instead nothing will happen to know
absolutely they labored our ATV destroy
yeah he's really good your fire you
yeah
huh
there's the other one is it this is
going great the dog the dog as well
isn't trying to be the big tree is it it
just is what it is nobody just means
what it but it is what it is it makes
this what it has that it is what it is
and it doesn't mogul complain about
there there's not jealous of the big
tree there there was a guy called Darwin
and there was a guy called run by this
guy called Darwin and a guy called
rumble yeah and a guy called Rumble came
up with this wonderful idea
cooperative anticipates now cooperative
interdependence means that the my RFP
the trees there I breath feeds me yet
we've got this relationship so I've got
relationship of the trees the waters in
my blood is the same as the water in the
rain cycle I've got a relationship I've
got a relationship with the whole of the
planet that I live on the food I eat is
the mineral Kingdom is the land that it
grows on if I toxifying poison the whole
of the planet for a short-term gain i'm
toxifying and poisoning myself by poison
the rains and poisoning the water I
drink but poison the air I breathe I'm
poisoning all of it so how is it that my
short-term financial gain can be worth
throwing away my long-term environmental
future what why are you competitive
because you're trained from year dot to
get an A right get an A - well Excel
knows be know vest that you are we are
winter its Darwin look at rumble look at
the fact that we're actually together
where we are all as you say we're all
walk at the moment where a parasitic
organism that's dividing a toast planet
of its ability at support life we need
to become a symbiotic life form the
support in the life of his host planet
this is a mental health problem that
we're in denial often
Peter self-centered on their people
xiri therein lies the real root we been
educated that way yeah in boxing and
that behavior is rewarded every step who
rises up the ranks of organizations and
governments and corporations but once
the ruthless motherfuckers who will do
anything and stamp on anyone to get
their right and so what we end up with
the world run by psychopaths and
criminals yeah what we are though is in
stone X though next time the new all you
know living is you know hunter-gatherer
utterly egalitarian well it but no it
was one Dalek fighting for dominance for
the up no it was two tribes probably any
that was another way they would kill
each other well they're very rated slave
the other Tommy one never really knows
cuz one wasn't there but according to
what I've read very very rarely actually
real conflict is not any you look in the
animal you use the animal kingdom before
yeah what happens when two stags are
facing off they swear at they're very
very very rare that two males when
they're fighting for dollars actually
fight yeah they put up a show and they
snarl a may growl and they swag their
asses or whatever but it's very rare
they actually come into physical
conflict one will usually back down
janata me and so it's a show of strength
rather than an actual battle and it
usually ends there in the animal kingdom
right there was a lot of trading between
the tribals and if there really had an
argue
then they have to kill each other
because there was no chord there was a
word if I made it wasn't really training
it was just a sharing of it you know I
know how to do this you know how to do
that let's exchange ideas
anybody wasn't like a trade it's just
that everyone's benefit acquire new
skills and new knowledge and young
tribes will amalgamate because they you
know they understood on some level that
this widened the gene pool as well right
and so this made them you know I'm a
Brazilian how exactly exactly money is
the money stuff we brought in so that we
could have a standing army before we did
that the people that would be in the
army would be the same people that grow
the crops that do all the other work in
society so when the two armies met more
often than not they had sent forward a
champion from each side the two people
ever might call for solution and the
decision would be made by those two
people fighting and the two armies would
go back to whatever it was they were
doing before right when we invented
money we had the ability to have an
expandable and expendable force a group
of people that were there
Julien truth simply to take life and
then the army that could just take life
and it didn't matter how many you lose
because you just buy some more could go
up against a group that had to feed
themselves had to hunt together had to
do all the other bits so decide that had
the big armies that had nothing else to
do could kill all of the others take
over their space and enslaving life and
that's who now runs the world the people
that have the big armies actually know
like you want us to delete our
promotions like we'd like Kremers
move-in father because they are in
Hangzhou so don't get rid of greed just
instead and spirit instead of focusing
your greed to in here I'm greedy for
little me transfer our greeter out there
I'm greedy to give I'm greedy to care
I'm greedy to solve this problem oh it's
not greed it's where it's Chloe turn it
inside out you know in green now becomes
in our stomach we need to lift it to our
heart and give instead of being greedy
to take that's always actually the same
thing you just doing the other way
various I mean that's basically
basically that's it I was thinking about
the questions before when you talked
about what should we do instead of money
and how do we actually get motivation to
build like if you want to build a
factory why do you want to build that
factory if the exact factory is for your
own gain people will have to have money
to be able to build it for you but it's
a but everybody if that if if you're
going to build a factory or perhaps a
hospital that we gain that other people
will gain from that we probably may be
here it'll help progress because that
will be the inspiration
and I'm real sorry different incentives
will arise you know what I mean you'll
gain status for different reasons I see
you know yeah I'm joined in halfway
through yeah so nice to get bits and
pieces you were here last week weren't
here or two weeks ago I remember you
yeah yeah yeah the money system now
right well no I think it succeeded
beautifully more designs give to enslave
a population yeah it succeeded
fantastically well well apparently not
actually the first of all through money
which normal are clearly heavier have
been hunter-gathering and once we've
broken up into tribes that were fighting
each other we did the bartering thing to
be able to trade with other tribes which
obviously caused more problems
well again again William taking
something that wasn't ours yeah claiming
it as ours and using it to manipulate
the minds of others okay but obviously
we're not going back know the ideas to
get away from trade in that sort of
sense
all together you know amazing Dee
proposed a collaboration collaboration
operation okay cooperation I think it's
impossible to achieve with our current
mindset I believe it's impossible yet
impossible to achieve with money the
solution remains
correct correct paying that debt you
know most families now you've got both
people out working 50-hour weeks pay for
child care never get to see their kids
they're always tired when they do see
their kids you know what I mean this is
not life they have stolen our lives from
it it doesn't have to be like this but
as I've said a couple of times
Solutions are not going to come from the
top down those one percent at the top
they love it the way things are they are
very happy we think it is up to us to
find grassroots way of making that
irrelevant you know start purifying your
own wall to grow some of your own
vegetables make sure when you buy meat
if you must eat meat make sure when you
buy meat but it is coming from a farm
where they look after their animals you
know what I mean don't buy into the
whole mass production thing
do what you can everybody can do
something most people can't do
everything but everybody can do
something so figure out what you can do
and start doing it now sorry you did you
want to say to me
I know there's a city in India where the
the government ships in the middle of it
but the whole city is actually keeping
them tell Galway and the money doesn't
leave the city right my circulates
within the city of Bristol pounds
they've got something here like in like
that in Bristol risk Bristol pounds yeah
it's a scheme for a local currency to
buy Bristol pounds for real pounds
they're worth the same as real bounce
but Bristol pounds can only be spent in
Bristol so it keeps money generated by
the local economy in the local economy
it doesn't go out to the big
corporations and correct that that's
another step on the road that's another
possibility as a transition step is that
you know anyone can start a currency
autonomy and it can be accepted on
whatever terms that current IVA text on
it can be used as a way to raise finance
to start a particular project and when
the project is complete then the
currency dies because it's done it job's
killing me and so you have hundreds of
currencies all running at the same time
popping in and out of existence being
created being destroyed all the time and
you know there's equivalency between
them it's a it's a complicated but
actually really beautiful elegant idea
it completely turns the idea of money on
its head it makes it work for us instead
of us working for it
Universal I think it I think it's an
excellent idea for a transitional step
remove people in slavery right take the
class slavery immediately and I think I
believe it don't you get like if you
have Universal let's get going get slave
because place and the one that's
controller I mean they're doing some
studies on right now there's there's to
kit there's two schools of thought on
this and until you try it you never
really know one school of thought is but
if you just give people the means to
live they don't have to do anything
exchange so just sit around stroking
their penises all day long you know they
but I like one thing on that they can
control their mouth of it so it would
just be it's a basic income right it's a
basic income it provides you the basic
you think like it's at all not a luxury
lifestyle right now later I face so you
don't have to work to get food and
shelter and heating you know what I mean
but you are still free to work and go
out there and own money but you don't
lose your income if you start earning
money that's the thing it's not like the
benefit that you knew when you start
earning it's everybody gets it over
ritual for you are everybody gets at
universal basic income right the other
school of thought is that if you free
people from having to go to shit jobs
every day if you know four six pounds an
hour or whatever and having to work
50-hour weeks just to pay the red if you
free people and then they will start
just doing other things they will stop
coming up with other ways to occupy
their time and they will start creating
blogs music pictures you know inventions
whatever and you know you now free
people up to follow things that they
actually want to do a very wise man once
said if you have to pay money to someone
to do something the job probably wasn't
worth doing in
so yeah I think and they try it right
now yeah they're giant Finland they're
trying in Scotland and they're trying
it's summer in Africa as well yeah yeah
please don't I mean that's even worse of
money as a control mechanism for society
so money is a cool right I agree with
you come from money
you know money to some extent no it's
not it's not a question really is if it
is how is this not play a big talk
because interest on make right and he
only benefits the rich I agree to that
to an extent in Islam how does your
claim
how would you say your views were
different to Islamic visiting and user
instance and so most Jannetty for many
hundreds of years and promote financing
and trade you're trying to see as a
transition as a transitional step but I
really do believe long term we have to
get away from the whole thing of money
and profit altogether and we have to
learn how to just just collaborate you
know the means you help each other out
to the Islamic music financing in three
how do you ban where you've an interest
and uses yeah as a as a first step as a
first step banning interest banning debt
based money burning usury and debt based
money I think I'll be dealing I think
I'd be an excellent yeah I bet but again
I would stress again with long term
that's just a transitional step in the
long term goal getting away from money
altogether yeah I really really believe
that has to be sustainability wide long
term good of humankind wise so money we
should be enrolled with rewarding
for me right yeah but what about
different what about different rewards
give me good have you okay
let me try something out if you can
afford it next time you all pass the
homeless guy next so no no spongy I'm
just saying next time your parts a
homeless guy that moves you in some way
that you like the look I would ever you
know sometimes you just feel a kinship
with someone yeah okay instead of giving
him a pound or two
give him a 20 pound note and experience
with upon his face that's why that's
your motivation right because you've
made someone else you make someone
else's life better by doing something
more than by giving your labor by
helping them out by giving them an idea
whatever you've made someone else's life
better
that feels good it feels a lot better
than a thousand put in the bank honestly
it's really really good and until people
get their mind set away from I must be
rewarded with money no but I'm saying
they're used to getting a burger they
used to getting a pound yeah if you give
them something for a homeless person
right now the best thing you can give me
is money right absolutely absolutely and
listen I know it's not helping them
long-term I get that but you know what
today they've had a good days you know I
mean I can't help them long-term you
know what I mean that's the best part I
suppose I could take it take it you know
give a room in my house or think I
father could do that yeah but you know
I'm not judging if he wants to go and
spend it on drugs we go spending on
drugs I'm not going to be judging the
guy you know but you're 13 pence worth
of heroin that we'd buy from somebody in
Afghanistan well timing in other
countries were three and equation
so if it was completely legal and
transported but wholesale boy government
or whatever down in pay want to okay
shopping you why your heroin fix on
there Amen if you got into a really bad
habit in my course of 26 papers yeah 300
walls and Quinn's 901 e so he was
spending a bottleneck on driving
recently in the illegal black bond is a
generating system where he didn't see
criminality as to a driver now you're
gonna be there's no way anybody can
afford those prices yeah thanks so we
have an awful lot of crime like the
first related to is probably something
winter Speakers was perfectly legal and
it was only illegal to private or any
really care yeah if you're going to sell
alcohol and sell tobacco sell drugs at
the same time of course that yeah but it
shouldn't be allowed profit on people
can be so why not breaking on our
connection wider I don't like you I
don't wanna break mankind amazing so
it's so lose it over the legal system to
motel to some support of all the hood I
was wounded Aggie
kind of in scary if you need prayer even
respondent way of saying who knew
Singapore history formation enjoy having
our pipeline we are thinking what you
read well they were okay good night we
come people will help me know so all of
history we know I think we know history
we don't know so we educate our children
to main come from our history correct
there's the comfortable weather bound
and so that my children will make a
history for I think wrong step into our
history so we think repeating our same
mistake over and over again because we
want to repeat the comfortable place to
be it we don't want to step in to give
of ourselves
a bus over there breathing
be peaceful
if we change the way that we live
because at the moment we claim the
ownership over this whole planet eight
hours if we can then to give the planet
back to all of life say it was never
ours in first place we made a terrible
mistake a long time ago and since then
we've been as it were living in sin
because we've been taking something that
wasn't ours and using it to the
detriment of all of life if we can so
yeah yeah yeah